原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/PwBoepMtjoY
原视频发布日期：20201113
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And it's been an interesting night for SpaceX fans.
对SpaceX的粉丝来说 这个夜晚很有趣
Well I'm not talking about Elon probably having coronavirus.
好吧 我不是指Elon可能感染新冠
I hope he recovers just fine
我希望他能很好地恢复
but yeah no we're talking about the drama over in Boca Chica related to SN8,
但当然这是指在博卡奇卡发生的关于SN8的麻烦事
the prototype Starship vehicle
SN8是Starship原型机
which is the first one fully assembled
而且是第一个完全组装好的
and was you know getting prepared for flight.
而现在正准备进行试飞
So SN8 if you've been keeping track
那么SN8 如果你一直在关注这件事
it's the first one that uses the new alloy.
就会知道 它是第一个使用新合金的原型机
They pressure tested it up and they rolled it out to the pad in October.
SN8进行了压力测试 并在10月移动到发射台
They did a test firing of all three engines without the nosecone attached on October 20th.
10月20日 没有装上鼻锥的SN8进行了一次三发动机静态点火测试
Then they rolled out a nosecone and attached it.
之后 工作人员拉来一个鼻锥 并把它安装到了SN8上
And so the last few days they've been trying to test fire the engines with the nosecone attached.
那么在过去的几天里 他们一直在尝试在装有鼻锥的状态下对发动机进行点火测试
And it isn't just like a cosmetic nosecone on the front.
这个鼻锥不仅仅是装饰作用的
There's a critical part to this and that is the header tanks.
里面还包含一个关键的部分 那就是头部储罐
So the header tanks are smaller tanks that are supposed to feed the engines during the landing procedure.
那么 头部储罐是较小的(燃料)储罐 应该是在降落过程中为发动机提供燃料的
They only have a small amount of fuel.
其中只容纳少量的燃料
I believe it's something like 22 tons in the nose.
我觉得 头部储罐大概能容纳22吨的(液氧)
And maybe about eight tons in the middle.
而中部的(甲烷储罐)大概能容纳8吨
The reason they're so far apart is because they want to balance the center of mass for the vehicle.
两个小储罐相隔这么远是为了平衡航天器的质量中心
The reason they use these small tanks is that
而之所以用这样的小储罐
when the thing is in flight and it wants to perform this flip maneuver and re-light the engines
是因为在飞行中 Starship要进行翻转动作 并重新点燃发动机
it has to be sure that it can draw propellant from the tanks.
必须确保其能从储罐中汲取推进剂
And if you have the large tanks as the thing you know performs this flip maneuver
而如果使用大型储罐中的推进剂的时候 进行这个翻转动作
因为着陆的时候大储罐中大部分燃料都用光了，大部分体积中填充的都是气体
it'll cause the propellant to slosh around inside the larger tank.
这个动作就会导致推进剂在大罐子里乱窜
So by using smaller tanks they reduce the slosh
那么 通过使用较小的储罐 可以减少燃料晃动
and that reduces the amount of voids or bubbles that gets sucked into the engines.
这样可以减少被吸入发动机的空隙或者说气泡的数量
Because when you're pulling tons of fuel through the engines very rapidly and you hit a bubble
因为在发动机快速地抽取大量燃料的时候 一旦遇到气泡
that can destroy your turbo pumps right.
就会破坏涡轮泵 对吧
It can really damage things.
它真的会造成损坏
So they've been trying to demonstrate that the new SN8 prototype can light the engines from wednesday.
那么 从周三起 SpaceX一直在对SN8这个新的原型机进行发动机点火试验
We had a test fire and it looked great.
其中有一次很好的点火试验
There were a lot of sparks that went flying.
有很多火花飞了出来
And that immediately caused consternation for tank watchers.
这立刻引起了储罐观察者的不安
There was lots of live streams of course you know Everyday Astronauts and NASASpaceflight.
当然有很多现场直播 你知道的 比如每日宇航员和NASASpaceflight
I was sort of sitting there looking at this
我当时差不多是坐在那儿正看着呢
and drawing lines back from the sparks to figure out where they came from.
之后就从火花上画出线条 以找出它们的来源
It looked like they were all converging on a point underneath the rocket.
看起来它们都汇聚在火箭下面的一个点上
It also looked like the they were bright until the engine sort of stopped burning
它们看起来也很亮 直到发动机停止点火
and the illumination was reduced and then they faded out.
发动机的亮度下降 之后这些火花就逐渐消失
So their illumination their brightness was correlated with the brightness of the engine.
那么这些火花的亮度与发动机的亮度相关
That meant that they weren't like hot things that were you know emitting light on their own.
这意味着它们并不像自发光的很热的物质一样
And so most people believe based on this that it was debris very likely bits of concrete or tiles
那么大多数人都因此认为 这是碎片 很可能是混凝土或地砖的碎片
which are used underneath the vehicle to protect the surface from the heat of the rocket engine.
也就是那些放在火箭下方 用来保护地面不受其发动机热量的影响的材料
So that that meant that there wasn't the rocket being damaged
所以这意味着火箭并没有损坏
but there is concern when you have anything like that that's throwing debris off at high speed
但你会担心 这样高速抛出的碎片
what happens if some of the debris comes back and hits under the vehicle that could be a bad thing.
掉落下来 砸到了下面的火箭
But I guess they went and said okay everything's fine.
但我觉得他们应该到现场查看过了 觉得没什么问题
They went for another test the following day last night
于是第二天晚上进行了第二次测试
and that was even more spectacular. It looked like two engines fired.
而这就更壮观了 看起来就像是两台发动机都点火了
we also saw some sparks again.
我们又看到了一些火花
So we started to wonder what was going on then we saw something dripping from underneath the rocket
正当我们还在搞清楚火花是怎么回事的时候 就看到火箭下面有东西在滴下
who aren't sure if this is like some sort of cryogenic liquid
谁也不知道这是不是某种低温液体
but it probably wasn't because we didn't see huge amounts of gas being produced or vapor being produced.
但它可能不是 因为我们没有看到大量的那种 气体或蒸汽
It might be that that was bits of the engine
而滴落的可能是发动机的一些部件
because Elon came on twitter very quickly and said We've had a bit of a problem.
因为Elon很快就在推特上说 我们遇到了一点问题
Looks like we've lost all pneumatic pressure in the vehicle.
看起来Starship内部已经失压
And it looks like one of the engines has probably had some sort of problem.
同时 其中一台发动机可能出了点问题
It might have you know blown up its test manifold as you know intake manifold or blown up a pre-burner
它可能炸毁了测试歧管 或者说输液歧管 或者也可能炸毁了一个预燃器
or something energetic has damaged the engine and has also damaged the pneumatic system.
或者说是某些高能物质损坏了发动机 也损坏了加压系统
The danger with that
这种情况下的危险是
is that the valves that control propellant flow throughout the vehicle are pneumatically actuated
在整个航天器中 控制推进剂流动的阀门都是气压驱动的
So they were stuck with a vehicle where they couldn't open the valves to reduce the pressure
那么这些液体被困在航天器中 无法通过打开阀门来降低压力
That header tank had tons of liquid oxygen in it
而头部储罐中有大量的液氧
and it was heating up and as it heats up that oxygen boils
它被(环境空气)加热 在加热以后 液氧就会沸腾
and that increases the pressure inside that tank.
这会增加了储罐内的压力
We've seen that these tanks can handle like seven or eight bar of pressure
我们已经知道 这些储罐可以承受7或8巴的压力
but we've also seen what happens when these tanks exceed their pressure and fail
但我们也知道 这些储罐被加压到超过其可承受压力而失效时的后果
and there was some real concern that this tank might fail and destroy the prototype.
而在这种情况下 就会担心储罐无法继续承压 (爆炸)并摧毁原型机
We did find out also Elon revealed that yes there was a burst disk
我们也发现 Elon透露 (储罐上配备)有爆破隔膜
and they were hoping that would pop.
他们希望这个隔膜会爆裂
A burst disc is a sheet of metal that you put into the pipe and it blocks the pipe
爆破隔膜是一种金属片 你把它放进管子里 就会挡住管子
but it's got a pattern usually scratched onto it like an X-shape
但它的图案通常被刮成X形
and they cut that just to a specific depth
并切到一个特定的深度
so that when the pressure on one side hits a certain amount
使之在一侧的压力达到一定程度时
it'll cause the disc to pop reliably.
隔膜就会可靠地爆炸
But there's a bit of slop in there
但有点糟糕的是
and there was also concern that maybe the welding on the new tank wasn't perfectly up to standard.
比如新储罐的焊接工艺可能还没有完全达标
Because of course we've had issues here there and with previous ones
因为当然是以前也发生过这样的问题
so there was some real you know drama going on as we watch this rocket.
那么看着这枚火箭的直播的时候 是真的遇到了一些难以揣摩的麻烦
Hoping that the pressure would relieve via the burst disk rather than the whole nose popping off.
希望压力能通过爆破隔膜来缓解 而不是整个鼻锥都爆掉
Thankfully we did eventually see gas leaking out the top and we thought the day was saved.
幸运的是 我们最终看到气体从顶部泄漏出来 扭转了局面
And we've seen now that there are people back at the pad.
而我们现在已经看到 有人回到了发射台
I think the road closures have been lifted.
我想道路封锁已经被解除了
You know we've seen in the past
而你知道的 在以前
where they've had to wait a couple of days with a pressurized tanks on a vehicle.
为了等待Starship的储罐泄压 需要等上好几天
So this is actually a lot faster turnaround.
那么实际这次周转得更快
So as of right now we don't know the exact status
那么现在我们还不知道确切的状态
but it's presumed that they will at least need to replace an engine on SN8.
但据推测 他们至少需要更换一台SN8的发动机
Maybe something else got damaged we don't know.
也许还有什么别的东西也损坏了 但目前我们还不知道
If they do need to like scrap the entire vehicle
如果他们真的需要换掉整个航天器
there's an SN9 is already sitting in the high bay so it's getting ready.
也没问题 因为SN9已经放在高湾厂房了
If they do just replace an engine presumably,
如果他们真的只是要更换一个发动机
they'll have to do another round of test fires on the pad
他们只能在发射台上进行另外一轮点火测试
and then if everything's going fine
那么如果一切顺利
they will be able to then fly the vehicle up to 15 kilometers
就会进行15km的试飞
and have it drop down and light its engines and hopefully aim for the landing pad.
在下降时点燃发动机 同时希望能瞄准着陆台
Presumably when it's falling
大概在它下降的时候
they'll target it in such a way that it doesn't hit or have a chance of hitting anything important
它的飞行轨迹会确保其不会有机会命中任何重要的东西
that one might logically presume they're going to have it descend over the sea
人们可能会顺理成章地认为他们会让它降落在海面上
and then pull out of the dive and you'll land on the pad.
然后在俯冲中改出 并降落在发射台上
But I don't know exactly what that plan is
但我不知道具体的计划如何
It might be that it's easier for to have them aim for land
也许瞄准陆地的轨迹还是更容易一些
because then if it crashes it'll be easier for them to clean it up.
因为这样的话 如果它坠毁了 清理起来更方便
Yeah I don't know. All excitement down in Boca Chica.
是啊 我不知道 接下来的博卡奇卡还是会让人非常兴奋的
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]